Some years ago, I set out to try to understand
قبل بضع سنوات، بدأت أحاول التفكير
if there was a possibility to develop biofuels
إن كانت هناك إمكانية لتطوير الوقود الحيوي
on a scale that would actually compete with fossil fuels
بشكل يُمَكِّنُهُ من المنافسة الفعلية للوقود الحفري
but not compete with agriculture for water,
لكن دون منافسة الزراعة على مصادر المياه
fertilizer or land.
أو المخصبات أو الأرض.
So here's what I came up with.
و هذا ما توصلت إليه.
Imagine that we build an enclosure where we put it
تخيلوا أننا أنشأنا منطقة مسيجة سنضعها
just underwater, and we fill it with wastewater
على سطح الماء، وسنملؤها بالمياه العادمة
and some form of microalgae that produces oil,
وببعض أنواع الطحالب المجهرية المنتجة للدهون،
and we make it out of some kind of flexible material
ونستخرجها بواسطة نوع مرن من المواد
that moves with waves underwater,
التي تتحرك مع الأمواج تحت الماء،
and the system that we're going to build, of course,
والنظام الذي سننشئ، سيستخدم طبعا
will use solar energy to grow the algae,
الطاقة الشمسية لنمو الطحالب،
and they use CO2, which is good,
وستسخدم الكربون، وهو أمر جيد لنا،
and they produce oxygen as they grow.
بينما ستنتج الأوكسيجين كلما نمت.
The algae that grow are in a container that
كانت الطحالب التي تنمو موجودة بالمستوعب
distributes the heat to the surrounding water,
الذي يسخن المياه من حوله،
and you can harvest them and make biofuels
ويمكنكم جمعها لصنع الوقود الحيوي
and cosmetics and fertilizer and animal feed,
ومواد التجميل والسماد وغذاء للحيونات،
and of course you'd have to make a large area of this,
وبالطبع سيكون عليكم تخصيص مساحة كبيرة لذلك،
so you'd have to worry about other stakeholders
سيكون عليكم القلق بشأن الأطراف الأخرى
like fishermen and ships and such things, but hey,
كالصيادين والسفن وما إلى ذلك،
we're talking about biofuels,
لكن، نحن نتحدث هنا عن الوقود الحيوي،
and we know the importance of potentially getting
ونحن نعلم مدى أهمية الفرص التي
an alternative liquid fuel.
يوفرها الوقود البديل السائل.
Why are we talking about microalgae?
لماذا نحن نتحدث عن الطحالب المجهرية؟
Here you see a graph showing you the different types
تشاهدون هنا مبيانا يظهر لكم مختلف أنواع
of crops that are being considered for making biofuels,
المحاصيل التي أصبحت تعتبر مصدر لإنتاج الوقود الحيوي،
so you can see some things like soybean,
يمكنكم رؤية بعضها كفول الصويا،
which makes 50 gallons per acre per year,
الذي ينتج في السنة 3 براميل لكل هكتار
or sunflower or canola or jatropha or palm, and that
أو عباد الشمس أو الكانولا أو اليطروفـة أو النخيل
tall graph there shows what microalgae can contribute.
أما هذا العمود الطويل هنا يوضح بكم قد تساهم الطحالب المجهرية.
That is to say, microalgae contributes between 2,000
هذا لنوضح أن الطحالب المجهرية تساهم في السنة
and 5,000 gallons per acre per year,
بما بين 120 و300 برميل لكل هكتار،
compared to the 50 gallons per acre per year from soy.
مقابل 3 براميل في السنة لكل هكتار من الصويا.
So what are microalgae? Microalgae are micro --
فماذا نقصد بالطحالب المجهرية؟ إنها مجهرية
that is, they're extremely small, as you can see here
فهي جد صغيرة كما يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا هنا
a picture of those single-celled organisms
في صورة لتلك الكائنات الوحيدة الخلية
compared to a human hair.
مقارنة بشعرة إنسان.
Those small organisms have been around
وتواجدة هذه الكائنات الصغيرة منذ حوالي
for millions of years and there's thousands
ملايين السنين كما أن هناك آلاف
of different species of microalgae in the world,
الأنواع المختلفة من الطحالب المجهرية بالعالم،
some of which are the fastest-growing plants on the planet,
البعض منها هي أسرع النباتات نموا في الكوكب
and produce, as I just showed you, lots and lots of oil.
وتنتج كما أوضحت الكثير والكثير من الوقود.
Now, why do we want to do this offshore?
لماذا نحن بحاجة لإنشائها بعرض البحر؟
Well, the reason we're doing this offshore is because
السبب لقيامنا بذلك هو أنكم
if you look at our coastal cities, there isn't a choice,
إن نظرتم لمدننا الساحلية فليس أمامنا من خيار،
because we're going to use waste water, as I suggested,
لأننا سنستخدم المياه العادمة كما سبق واقترحت،
and if you look at where most of the waste water
وإن نظرتم لمكان تواجد معظم محطات معالجة المياه العادمة،
treatment plants are, they're embedded in the cities.
فستجدونها محشورة بقلب المدن.
This is the city of San Francisco, which has 900 miles
هذه مدينة سان فرانسيسكو التي يوجد تحتها حاليا
of sewer pipes under the city already,
1500 كلم من أنابيب الصرف الصحي،
and it releases its waste water offshore.
والتي تطلق مياهها العادمة بعرض البحر.
So different cities around the world treat their waste water
كل مدينة حول العالم تعالج مياهها العادمة
differently. Some cities process it.
بشكل مختلف. فبعضها تقوم بمعالجتها
Some cities just release the water.
وبعضها تطلقها فقط بمياه البحر.
But in all cases, the water that's released is
لكن في جميع الحالات، فإن المياه التي تطلق بالبحر هي
perfectly adequate for growing microalgae.
مناسبة تماما لنمو الطحالب المجهرية.
So let's envision what the system might look like.
دعونا إذا نتصور الشكل الذي قد يتخذه النظام.
We call it OMEGA, which is an acronym for
نسميه "اوميغا" وهو اختصار
Offshore Membrane Enclosures for Growing Algae.
لمشروع "أوفشور مومبران إنكلوزرس فور غروين ألغ"
At NASA, you have to have good acronyms.
في وكالة ناسا، يجب عليك أن تمتلك أسماء مختصرت جذابة.
So how does it work? I sort of showed you how it works already.
كيف تعمل؟ لقد أريتكم نوعا ما كيف تعمل.
We put waste water and some source of CO2
نضخ المياه العادمة وبعض ثنائي أكسيد الكربون
into our floating structure,
إلى داخل النظام العائم،
and the waste water provides nutrients for the algae to grow,
وتوفر المياه العادمة الغذاء للطحالب لتنمو،
and they sequester CO2 that would otherwise go off
وتمتص ثاني أكسيد الكربون الذي كان سينطلق
into the atmosphere as a greenhouse gas.
بالغلاف الجوي كغاز مسبب للاحتباس الحراري.
They of course use solar energy to grow,
وبالطبع، فإنها تستخدم حرارة الشمس للنمو،
and the wave energy on the surface provides energy
بينما تعمل حركة الأمواج بالسطح على توفير الطاقة
for mixing the algae, and the temperature
لخلط الطحالب، أما الحرارة
is controlled by the surrounding water temperature.
فيتحكم بها حرارة المياه المحيطة بها.
The algae that grow produce oxygen, as I've mentioned,
وكما أشرت، فإن الطحالب التي تنمو تنتج الأوكسيجين
and they also produce biofuels and fertilizer and food and
والوقود الحيوي والسماد والغذاء
other bi-algal products of interest.
ومنتجات أخرى مهمة من الطحالب.
And the system is contained. What do I mean by that?
كما أن النظام مغلق. فماذا أقصد بذلك؟
It's modular. Let's say something happens that's
إنه مكون من وحدات مستقلة. فلنفترض أن شيئا
totally unexpected to one of the modules.
غير متوقع يحدث لإحدى الوحدات.
It leaks. It's struck by lightning.
كتسرب مثلا أو كأن يصيبها البرق.
The waste water that leaks out is water that already now
المياه العادمة التي تتسرب هي في الأصل
goes into that coastal environment, and
جزء من تلك البيئة الساحلية
the algae that leak out are biodegradable,
كما أن الطحالب المتسربة قابلة للتحلل،
and because they're living in waste water,
وبما أنها تعيش بالمياه العادمة
they're fresh water algae, which means they can't
فإنها طحالب مياه عذبة مما يعني أنها
live in salt water, so they die.
لا تستطيع العيش بالمياه المالحة وبالتالي ستموت.
The plastic we'll build it out of is some kind of
البلاستيك الذي سنصنع به الوحدات هو نوع
well-known plastic that we have good experience with, and
نعرفه جيدا ولنا معه تجارب جيدة
we'll rebuild our modules to be able to reuse them again.
كما أننا سنصنع وحداتنا بشكل يمَكِّنُ من إعادة استخدامها.
So we may be able to go beyond that when thinking about
يمكننا تخطي كل هذا عندما نفكر في
this system that I'm showing you, and that is to say
هذا النظام الذي أعرضه أمامكم، مما يعني
we need to think in terms of the water, the fresh water,
أننا بحاجة للتفكير في أهمية الماء، الماء العذب،
which is also going to be an issue in the future,
الذي سيصبح بدوره مشكة بالمستقبل،
and we're working on methods now
وسنعمل الآن على تطوير طرق
for recovering the waste water.
لاستعادة الماء العذب من المياه العادمة.
The other thing to consider is the structure itself.
الشيء الثاني الذي يجب أخذه بالحسبان هو البنية نفسها.
It provides a surface for things in the ocean,
فهي توفر سطح للأحياء الموجودة بالبحر،
and this surface, which is covered by seaweeds
وهذا السطح الذي غُطِّيَ بالأعشاب البحرية
and other organisms in the ocean,
وكائنات أخرى بالبحر،
will become enhanced marine habitat
ستصبح ملاذا بحريا
so it increases biodiversity.
أي سترفع من التنوع البيئي.
And finally, because it's an offshore structure,
وبما أنه نظام بعرض البحر
we can think in terms of how it might contribute
يمكننا التفكير في الكيفية التي قد يساهم بها
to an aquaculture activity offshore.
في تطوير الزراع المائية بعرض البحر.
So you're probably thinking, "Gee, this sounds
لربما أنتم الآن تتساءلون، "يبدو أنها فكرة جيدة.
like a good idea. What can we do to try to see if it's real?"
ما الذي يمكننا القيام به لنرى إن كان ذلك ممكنا؟"
Well, I set up laboratories in Santa Cruz
أنشأت مختبرات بسنتا كروز
at the California Fish and Game facility,
بمرافق كاليفورنيا فيش أند غيم
and that facility allowed us to have big seawater tanks
وقد وفرت لنا هذه المرافق صهاريج مياه بحر كبيرة
to test some of these ideas.
لاختبار بعض تلك الأفكار.
We also set up experiments in San Francisco
وقمنا أيضا بتجارب بإحدى المحطات الثلاث
at one of the three waste water treatment plants,
بسان فرانسيسكو لمعالجة المياه العادمة
again a facility to test ideas.
مرة أخرى مرفق لاختبار تلك الأفكار.
And finally, we wanted to see where we could look at
نحن الآن نحاول معرفة الطريق الذي سنتبعه
what the impact of this structure would be
ما هو التأثير الذي قد يتركه النظام
in the marine environment, and we set up a field site
على البيئة البحرية، لدى أنشأنا موقع اختبار بمكان
at a place called Moss Landing Marine Lab
يدعى المختبر البحري بموس لاندينغ
in Monterey Bay, where we worked in a harbor
بخليج مونتيري حيث نعمل بميناء
to see what impact this would have on marine organisms.
لمعرفة مدى تأثيره على الكائنات البحرية.
The laboratory that we set up in Santa Cruz was our skunkworks.
كان المختبر الذي أنشأناه بسنتا كروز بمثابة عمل أولي.
It was a place where we were growing algae
كان ذلك الموقع الذي نزرع فيه الطحالب
and welding plastic and building tools
ونرمم فيه البلاستيك ونبني فيه الآليات
and making a lot of mistakes,
والذي ارتكبنا فيه الكثير من الأخطاء
or, as Edison said, we were
أو كما يقول اديسون،
finding the 10,000 ways that the system wouldn't work.
المكان الذي توصلنا فيه ل 10.000 طريقة لا تشغل النظام.
Now, we grew algae in waste water, and we built tools
نربي الطحالب في المياه العادمة ونبني الآليات
that allowed us to get into the lives of algae
التي تسمح لنا بالتعمق والتعرف على حياة الطحالب
so that we could monitor the way they grow,
والتي قد تسمح لنا بالتعرف على طريقة نموها
what makes them happy, how do we make sure that
ما الذي يجعلها تزدهر وكيف نتأكد بأننا
we're going to have a culture that will survive and thrive.
سنحصل على زراعة ستبقى على قيد الحياة وتزدهر.
So the most important feature that we needed to develop were these
أهم جانب كان علينا تطويره
so-called photobioreactors, or PBRs.
هو ما يدعى بالمفاعلات الحيوية الضوئية.
These were the structures that would be floating at the
كانت تلك الأنظمة التي ستطفوا على
surface made out of some inexpensive plastic material
سطح البحر مصنوعة من مادة بلاستيكية شيئا ما مُكَلِّفَة
that'll allow the algae to grow, and we had built lots and lots
ستسمح للطحالب بالنمو وقد صنعنا العديد من النماذج
of designs, most of which were horrible failures,
كانت أغلبها محاولات جد فاشلة
and when we finally got to a design that worked,
وعندما توصلنا في النهاية للنموذج الذي يعمل
at about 30 gallons, we scaled it up
بما يقارب 0,1 متر مكعب، عملنا على تكبيره
to 450 gallons in San Francisco.
ليصل ل 1,7 متر مكعب بسان فرانسيسكو.
So let me show you how the system works.
دعوني أريكم كيف يعمل النظام.
We basically take waste water with algae of our choice in it,
في البداية نأخذ المياه العادمة والطحالب التي نختار
and we circulate it through this floating structure,
ونجعلها تسري خلال النظام العائم،
this tubular, flexible plastic structure,
النظام البلاستيكي الأنبوبي والمرن
and it circulates through this thing,
فتسري خلاله
and there's sunlight of course, it's at the surface,
وبالطبع هناك أشعة الشمس أيضا، فهو يطفوا على السطح
and the algae grow on the nutrients.
والطحالب تنمو بفضل المغذيات.
But this is a bit like putting your head in a plastic bag.
فالأمر كوضع رؤوسكم بكيس بلاستيكي.
The algae are not going to suffocate because of CO2,
فالطحالب لن تختنق بفضل ثاني أوكسيد الكربون،
as we would.
كما يحدث لنا.
They suffocate because they produce oxygen, and they
فهي تختنق بسبب إنتاجها للأوكسجين،
don't really suffocate, but the oxygen that they produce
إلا أنها لا تختنق حقا، إلا أن الأوكسجين الذي تنتجه
is problematic, and they use up all the CO2.
يبقى مشكلا، فهي تستهلك كل ثاني أوكسيد الكربون.
So the next thing we had to figure out was how we could
لدى فالأمر الثاني الذي كان علينا حله هو
remove the oxygen, which we did by building this column
كيف نستخلص الأوكسجين الذي أنشأنا من أجله هذا الأنبوب
which circulated some of the water,
الذي يسري فيه القليل من الماء
and put back CO2, which we did by bubbling the system
ونعيد ضخ ثاني أوكسيد الكربون الذي نملأ به النظام
before we recirculated the water.
قبل أن نطلق فيه المياه.
And what you see here is the prototype,
وما تشاهدونه هنا اليوم هو نموذج أولي
which was the first attempt at building this type of column.
الذي كان أول محاولة لبناء مثل هذا النوع من الأنابيب.
The larger column that we then installed in San Francisco
وكان الأنبوب الذي أنشأناه بعدها بسان فرانسيسكو هو الأكبر
in the installed system.
بالنظام الذي سبق وأنشأناه.
So the column actually had another very nice feature,
وفي الحقيقة كان للأنبوب ميزة رائعة
and that is the algae settle in the column,
وهي أن الطحالب أصبحت تترسب في قاع الأنبوب
and this allowed us to accumulate the algal biomass
مما سمح لنا بجمع كتلة حيوية من الطحالب
in a context where we could easily harvest it.
في ظروف يسهل علينا فيها جمعها.
So we would remove the algaes that concentrated
فنجمع الطحالب التي تتكتل
in the bottom of this column, and then we could
بقاع الأنبوب لنقوم بعدها نحن
harvest that by a procedure where you float the algae
بحيث نقوم بجعلها تطفوا نحو السطح
to the surface and can skim it off with a net.
فنتمكن من ترشيحها بواسطة شبكة ونجمعها.
So we wanted to also investigate what would be the impact
إلا أننا أردنا معرفة مدى تأثيرهذا
of this system in the marine environment,
النظام على البيئة البحرية
and I mentioned we set up this experiment at a field site
وكما أشرت من قبل أنشأنا هذه التجربة على أرض الواقع
in Moss Landing Marine Lab.
بالمختبر البحري بموس لاندينغ.
Well, we found of course that this material became
وبالطبع وجدنا أن الطحالب تزدهر
overgrown with algae, and we needed then to develop
بكثرة وكنا بعدها بحاجة لتطوير
a cleaning procedure, and we also looked at how
طريقة للتنظيف، كما أننا راقبنا كيف
seabirds and marine mammals interacted, and in fact you
تتفاعل الطيور والثدييات البحرية، وأنتم الآن
see here a sea otter that found this incredibly interesting,
تشاهدون ثعلب الماء الذي يجد النظام جد مثير للاهتمام
and would periodically work its way across this little
والذي سيجد لنفسه طريقا من حين لأخر خلال هذا
floating water bed, and we wanted to hire this guy
السرير المائي العائم، ونحن نحاول استخدام هذا القوي
or train him to be able to clean the surface
أو تدريبه لينظف السطح الخارجي
of these things, but that's for the future.
للأنبوب، لكننا سنترك ذلك للمستقبل.
Now really what we were doing,
لكن ما الذي كنا نفعله حقا،
we were working in four areas.
كنا نعمل على 4 أصعدة.
Our research covered the biology of the system,
شَمِلَ بحثنا بيولوجيا النظام
which included studying the way algae grew,
الذي يهم دراسة طريقة نمو الطحالب
but also what eats the algae, and what kills the algae.
وأيضا ما تتغذى عليه أو ما قد يقتلها.
We did engineering to understand what we would need
قمنا بدراسات هندسية لمعرفة ما الذي نحتاجه
to be able to do to build this structure,
للتمكن من بناء هذا النظام
not only on the small scale, but how we would build it
ليس فقط بمقياس صغير، بل كيف يمكن أن نبنيه
on this enormous scale that will ultimately be required.
في هذا الحجم الضخم الذي سيطلب منا فيما بعد.
I mentioned we looked at birds and marine mammals
كما أشرت مسبقا، راقبنا الطيور والثدييات البحرية
and looked at basically the environmental impact
وبصفة عامة تأثير النظام على البيئة،
of the system, and finally we looked at the economics,
وفي النهاية البعد الاقتصادي،
and what I mean by economics is,
الذي أقصده بالبعد الاقتصادي هو،
what is the energy required to run the system?
ما هي الطاقة اللازمة لتشغيل النظام؟
Do you get more energy out of the system
هل سينتج النظام طاقة أكثر
than you have to put into the system
مما سيزود به
to be able to make the system run?
ليصبح تشغيله ممكنا؟
And what about operating costs?
وماذا عن تكاليف التشغيل؟
And what about capital costs?
وعن تكاليف الاستثمار فيه؟
And what about, just, the whole economic structure?
وماذا عن البنية الاقتصادية للنظام بشكل عام؟
So let me tell you that it's not going to be easy,
دعوني أخبركم بشيء، لن يكون الأمر سهلا،
and there's lots more work to do in all four
فما يزال هناك الكثير من العمل بالجبهات
of those areas to be able to really make the system work.
الأربع لنتمكن فعليا من جعل النظام يعمل.
But we don't have a lot of time, and I'd like to show you
لككنا لا نملك الكثير من الوقت وأود أن أريكم
the artist's conception of how this system might look
تصور لما سيبدو عليه النظام
if we find ourselves in a protected bay
إن نحن كنا بخليج محمي
somewhere in the world, and we have in the background
بمكان ما بالعالم، ولدينا في خلفية
in this image, the waste water treatment plant
الصورة محطة لمعالجة المياه العادمة
and a source of flue gas for the CO2,
ومصدر لضخ غاز ثاني أوكسيد الكربون،
but when you do the economics of this system,
لكن عند قيامكم بحساب الكلفة الاقتصادية للنظام
you find that in fact it will be difficult to make it work.
ندرك أنه في الواقع سيكون من الصعب جعل هذا النظام يعمل.
Unless you look at the system as a way to treat waste water,
إلا إذا اعتبرنا النظام طريقة لمعالجة المياه العادمة
sequester carbon, and potentially for photovoltaic panels
وحبس الكربون ولما لا لحمل ألواح الخلايا الشمسية
or wave energy or even wind energy,
أو لإنتاج الطاقة من الموج أو حتى من الرياح
and if you start thinking in terms of
فإن بدأتم بالتفكير بفرضية
integrating all of these different activities,
إدماج كل هذه الأنشطة المختلفة معا
you could also include in such a facility aquaculture.
سيمكنكم أيضا إدماج الزراعة المائية به بكل سهولة.
So we would have under this system a shellfish aquaculture
عندها سيكون لدينا تحت النظام مزارع لتربية المحار
where we're growing mussels or scallops.
حيث سنربي بلح البحر والأسقلوب.
We'd be growing oysters and things
سنكون قادرين على تربية المحار وأشياء أخرى
that would be producing high value products and food,
سيكون قادرا على إنتاج منتوجات وأغذية ذات جودة عالية
and this would be a market driver as we build the system
وسيكون هذا النظام محركا للسوق حيثما أنشئ
to larger and larger scales so that it becomes, ultimately,
ليكبر مع الوقت فيصبح بالنهاية
competitive with the idea of doing it for fuels.
منافسا لفكرة إنشاءه من أجل الوقود فقط.
So there's always a big question that comes up,
لكن يبقى سؤال واحد كبير،
because plastic in the ocean has got a really bad reputation
لأنه حاليا البلاستيك لديه سمعة جد سيئة بالبحر
right now, and so we've been thinking cradle to cradle.
لدى فكرنا من الألف إلى الياء.
What are we going to do with all this plastic that we're
ماذا سنفعل بكل ذلك البلاستيك الذي
going to need to use in our marine environment?
سنستخدمه ببيئتنا البحرية؟
Well, I don't know if you know about this,
لا أعلم إن كنتم تعرفون شيئا عن هذا الأمر
but in California, there's a huge amount of plastic
لكن بكاليفورنيا تستخدم كمية ضخمة من البلاستيك
that's used in fields right now as plastic mulch,
حاليا تستخدم بالحقول كبيوت لحماية المزروعات
and this is plastic that's making these tiny little greenhouses
وهو ذلك البلاستيك الذي يرفع من درجة حرارة
right along the surface of the soil, and this provides
التربة، ويوفر لنا الحرارة المناسبة
warming the soil to increase the growing season,
لتمديد فترة زراعة المحاصيل خارج وقتها،
it allows us to control weeds,
كما تسمح لنا بالتحكم بالأعشاب الضارة
and, of course, it makes the watering much more efficient.
وبالطبع، ترفع من فعالية السقي.
So the OMEGA system will be part
لدى سيصبح نظام أوميغا جزءا
of this type of an outcome, and that when we're finished
من هذا النوع من النتائج، وعندما سننتهي
using it in the marine environment, we'll be using it,
من استخدامه بالبيئة البحرية نأمل
hopefully, on fields.
في استخدامه بالحقول.
Where are we going to put this,
أين سنضعه
and what will it look like offshore?
وما الذي سيبدو عليه بعرض البحر؟
Here's an image of what we could do in San Francisco Bay.
هذه صورة عما يمكننا فعله في خليج سان فرانسيسكو.
San Francisco produces 65 million gallons a day
تنتج سان فرانسيسكو 250.00 متر مكعب يوميا
of waste water. If we imagine a five-day retention time
من المياه العذبة. أما إذا افترضنا أن النظام بحاجة
for this system, we'd need 325 million gallons
لفترة حفظ من 5 أيام فإننا سنحتاج للتعامل مع
to accomodate, and that would be about 1,280 acres
1,25 مليون متر مكعب، وهو ما يقارب 518 هكتار
of these OMEGA modules floating in San Francisco Bay.
من أنابيب أوميغا العائمة بخليج سان فرانسيسكو.
Well, that's less than one percent
وهذا أقل من 1 بالمئة
of the surface area of the bay.
من سطح مساحة الخليج.
It would produce, at 2,000 gallons per acre per year,
ستنتج في السنة ما يعادل 120 برميل للهكتار
it would produce over 2 million gallons of fuel,
ستنتج أكثر من مليوني برميل من الوقود
which is about 20 percent of the biodiesel,
أي حوالي 20 بالمئة من الديزل الحيوي
or of the diesel that would be required in San Francisco,
أو من الديزل الذي تستهلكه سان فرانسيسكو
and that's without doing anything about efficiency.
كل هذا دون العمل لتحقيق الفعالية.
Where else could we potentially put this system?
أين يمكننا أيضا إنشاء هذا النظام؟
There's lots of possibilities.
هناك الكثير من الإمكانيات.
There's, of course, San Francisco Bay, as I mentioned.
وبالطبع، هناك خليج سان فرانسيسكو الذي أشرت إليه
San Diego Bay is another example,
وكمثال أخر هناك خليج سان ديغو
Mobile Bay or Chesapeake Bay, but the reality is,
أوخليج موبايل أو حليج شيكسبير، ولكن الحقيقة هي
as sea level rises, there's going to be lots and lots
أن مع ارتفاع مستوى البحر سيكون هناك الكثير من
of new opportunities to consider. (Laughter)
الإمكانيات الجديدة التي ستتاح لنا. (ضحك)
So what I'm telling you about is a system
الذي أتحدث عنه هنا هو أنه نظام
of integrated activities.
متكامل من الأنشطة.
Biofuels production is integrated with alternative energy
فإنتاج الوقود الحيوي سيكون متكاملا مع الطاقات البديلة
is integrated with aquaculture.
التي بدورها ستكون متكاملة مع الزراعة المائية.
I set out to find a pathway
أردت أن أجد طريقة
to innovative production of sustainable biofuels,
مبتكرة لإنتاج الوقود الحيوي المستدام،
and en route I discovered that what's really required
وفي طريقي لذلك اكتشفت أن المطلوب من أجل
for sustainability is integration more than innovation.
الاستدامة هو التكامل بين أكثر من ابتكار.
Long term, I have great faith
لدي ثقة كبيرة على المدى البعيد
in our collective and connected ingenuity.
في إبداعنا الجماعي والمترابط.
I think there is almost no limit to what we can accomplish
أعتقد انه لا حدود لما يمكننا تحقيقه
if we are radically open
إن نحن انفتحنا بالكامل
and we don't care who gets the credit.
ولم نهتم بمن سينال الثناء.
Sustainable solutions for our future problems
الحلول المستدامة لمشاكلنا المستقبلية
are going to be diverse
ستكون متنوعة
and are going to be many.
وستكون عديدة.
I think we need to consider everything,
أعتقد أننا بحاجة للأخذ بعين الاعتبار كل شيء،
everything from alpha to OMEGA.
كل شيء من ألفا إلى أوميغا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Just a quick question for you, Jonathan.
كريس أندرسون: جوناثان سؤال سريع.
Can this project continue to move forward within
هل يمكن لهذا المشروع أن يستمر دون
NASA or do you need some very ambitious
الناسا أو أنكم بحاجة لبعض المستثمرين
green energy fund to come and take it by the throat?
الخضر الطموحين لكي يأخدوا بيدكم؟
Jonathan Trent: So it's really gotten to a stage now
جوناثان ترينت: لقد وصلنا اليوم لمرحلة في الناسا
in NASA where they would like to spin it out into something
حيث يريدون منا أن نعطيهم شيئا
which would go offshore, and there are a lot of issues
يمكن أن إطلاقه في عرض البحر، وهناك الكثير من المشاكل
with doing it in the United States because of limited
لتحقيقه بالولايات المتحدة بسبب قلة التصاريح
permitting issues and the time required to get permits
الممنوحة والوقت الضروري للحصول على
to do things offshore.
تصاريح لإنشاء أشياء بعرض البحر.
It really requires, at this point, people on the outside,
في مرحلتنا هذه نحتاج حقا لمساعدة من أشخاص من خارج المشروع.
and we're being radically open with this technology
ولقد كنا منفتحين بالكامل مع هذه التكنولوجيا
in which we're going to launch it out there
بحيث كنا على استعداد لإطلاق المشروع هنا
for anybody and everybody who's interested
لأي أحد ولكل من هو مهتم
to take it on and try to make it real.
لحمل المشروع وأن يحاول إخراجه لأرض الواقع.
CA: So that's interesting. You're not patenting it.
ك أ: هذا مثير للاهتمام. أنتم لم تسعوا لتسجيل براءت اختراعه.
You're publishing it.
بل تحاولون تعميمه.
JT: Absolutely.
ج ت: تماما.
CA: All right. Thank you so much.
ك أ: جيد. شكرا جزيلا.
JT: Thank you. (Applause)
ج ت: شكرا لك. (تصفيق)